Did a recession begin in the United
States in October of 2025? Not just the
forgot how to grow style that we've been
grappling with for the last couple
years, but a full-blown all-out NBR
style recession. Take a look at the data
and charts that we'll show you in this
video. Let's see what you think about
all this. And keep in mind, the numbers
that we're going to be going through and
focusing on are those that the NBR
itself uses when deciding the business
cycle question. What makes these numbers
particularly powerful and compelling is
both what they're showing and where they
come from. We're talking about private
sector income, the most essential part
of every economy. This is why the NBR
itself looks to this specific data when
it comes time to decide the recession
question. Now, we've been talking about
and documenting job losses for months
now, flat beverage. The data showing all
of that comes from the Bureau of Labor
Statistics. These income estimates come
from a completely separate agency, the
Bureau of Economic Analysis. They're
looking at the same thing, but from a
completely different perspective, yet
arriving at the same place the BLS data
already did. In other words, some of the
most critical macroeconomic evidence
that we have agrees. Something big
changed late last year and changed in a
way that looks an awful lot like
previous business cycle peaks.
There's this growing sense and growing
evidence for the classic historical
energy shock case. Like I said, this is
data that started long before we got to
March in the Iran conflict. Steve, you
saw the numbers as I did. We have income
data that came out, GDP, the savings
rate, you know, personal income and
spending from the Bureau of Economic
Analysis. What's most compelling about
it to me, you know, we've been talking
about the establishment survey and the
household survey, the BLS labor data for
quite some time. The BEA is a completely
separate outfit. They track income from
an economy perspective and they say,
"You know what? It kind of looks like a
recession here."
>> Yeah, Jeff, and this is like the
clearest sign of a K-shaped economy that
we've had yet. For For some Americans,
very clearly, they're in a recession.
They don't have enough money. Prices are
going up. They're struggling. They're
looking at the labor market. If they're
trying to get more hours or maybe even a
part-time job, the opportunities aren't
there. And yet, for others, they're
saying, "Well, wait a minute. The stock
market's up. You know, I'm getting huge
bonuses. I'm out spending money. I don't
see it." And that's one of the
challenges here, particularly when you
go into energy shocks, is it doesn't
affect everybody across the board. You
start to see it happen at the bottom.
And then, you know, what do we know that
we hear from retailers like Walmart
saying, "Hey, you know, business is
starting to boom here." Except, all of a
sudden, people are getting very mindful
how much gas they purchase. And we heard
from Home Depot and Lowe's are saying,
"Wait a minute. People, all of a sudden,
in April, cut back their spending." So,
we start to see more and more evidence
that incomes really do matter here. And
as you said, the evidence is the savings
rate. You're talking about what's been
really propping up the economy, tax
refund checks, and people dipping into
their savings. The challenge is, at some
point, there is a line in the sand where
people say, "Look, my savings have now
dropped to a certain level. I have to
cut my spending." And next thing you
know, we start to see that K-shaped
economy start to collapse together.
>> Yeah, the K-shaped economy, what really
happens is the bottom part of that
K-shape gets bigger and bigger and
bigger as more people fall out of the
top and into the bottom, which is what a
lot of Americans either are feeling or
they're afraid of. That's one reason why
consumer sentiment is so bad, because
consumers are worried. They think,
"Okay, maybe I'm in the upper part of
the K today and things are looking
looking all right." But if if this
continues to go like it is, I'm afraid
I'm going to end up in the bottom part,
and then what am I going to do?" You're
You're absolutely right, Steve. The
personal savings rate fell to 2.6%. One
of the reasons it fell to 2.6% because,
as we started the show with, income was
terrible. Income was absolutely
terrible. The top line income, personal
income in nominal terms, was a zero.
Zero growth rate in April. Now, some of
that had to do with the adjustment and
some of the data and details, but we
have seen personal income in nominal
terms weaken over the last six, seven,
eight months, which is right around the
time that the, you know, flat beverage
job loss economy showed up to begin
with. So, once again, we have the income
data from the Bureau of Economic
Analysis saying, "You know what? The job
losses, they weren't huge job losses,
but they you know, somewhat of job
losses that were taking place over here
in the Bureau of Labor Statistics, we're
seeing the same things from a different
perspective." And then it just goes from
there. If nominal incomes are dropping,
they're not crashing, they're not
falling off a cliff, but they are
definitely there's definitely an
inflection and shift going on here. If
nominal incomes are dropping, as we
know, consumers don't respond to that
right away. Like you said, Steve, they
use their savings, they use other funds,
in this case, the tax refunds to, you
know, they pull back a little bit, but
not nearly as much as incomes pull back.
And so, spending starts to lag incomes,
which means the savings rate just
absolutely tumbles, which is exactly
what the data showed. The savings rate
for April was down to 2.6%,
which is the lowest since 2022. And back
in 2022, savings were low because prices
were assuming soaring ahead so much
more. These are numbers that you usually
see in the early stages of a recession.
So, the savings rate, like the income
data, like the jobs data,
suggests something big shifted. Not in
March and April with the energy shock,
but way back in 2025. We were talking
about this at the time. It looked like,
"Hey, something big is going on in the
economy." And now we're getting more and
more confirmation that that really was
the case. Before we go on with our video
today, let me ask you a question. What
if your gold could actually pay you
every single month in more gold? That's
what today's video sponsor, Monetary
Metals, lets you do.
And here's how it works. You still own
the gold, it's still in your name, it's
fully insured, but instead of just
sitting there doing nothing, it actually
starts working for you. Monetary Metals
has built a system that turns idle gold
into productive gold, earning real yield
paid in physical gold, not dollars. No
selling, no trading, no converting. You
keep your gold and every month you get
more of it. It's a simple idea, but it
solves a big problem. If gold is money,
it should act like money, and now it
finally can.
If you're a long-term gold holder
looking for a smarter way to store
value, check them out at
monetary-metals.com/snyder.
Again, that's
I highly recommend booking a call with
them today to see if they're the right
fit for you. We thank Monetary Metals
for their sponsorship, and now let's get
back to the rest of our video.
>> Yeah, absolutely, because Jeff, you
know, we talk about stagflation, and
here's clear evidence. You see rising
consumer prices, and what are we seeing?
Now, hours worked are they're holding up
relatively. I mean, they're not dropping
off the cliff, but average hourly
earnings continue to tick down. Then you
inflation adjust them, and all of a
sudden it's like, "Well, wait a minute,
they turn negative." So, you start to
think about this for a second, say,
"Wait a minute, why is spending
dropping?" It's because relative to
inflation, the average worker is falling
behind, and and we know that's getting
up into the middle class. Now, here's
some anecdotal evidence I got just this
last week. I'd take one of my cars in
for service, and you know, of course
when you're there, the uh salesmen love
to talk to you, and being in the uh kind
of salesman whatnot, Jeff, I love to
talk to sales people because I ask them
questions about how business is. And one
of the guys said, "Hey, you know what?
Business isn't really that good right
now." And I said, "Well, is that
normal?" He says, "No." He says, "Here's
the deal. What everybody perceives as
their Christmas time, our Christmas time
is tax refund checks because that's when
people can come in, they may be a little
upside down, maybe they need a little
down payment, and they've got the check.
This is our boom time. He says it's the
worst I've seen in the six years I've
been in this business.
>> Yeah, that's not surprising, especially
when, you know, again, that's the that's
I think the the point here is the income
data is not a warning, it's
confirmation. It's telling us I I hate
to say what we already know or what at
least at least what we were already
suspecting. That's what makes it more
compelling because it's a deeper source
of data, it comes from a very different
agency, and it really shows some
alarming results. Let me throw some more
at you here. Again, real personal income
excluding transfer receipts. This is a
key critical data series on income. It's
It's one that even the NBER itself uses.
Not that that's an endorsement or
anything. I mean, they're a bunch of
economists, we don't really care what
they do, but even economists say, "Hey,
this is one we need to pay attention
to." When the NBER gets around, their
you know, the business cycle dating
committee, when they start thinking
about recessions, this is one of the
first numbers that they pull out. And
what it has shown is a contraction in
income, price adjusted income because
it's just like Steve said, incomes are
flat on nominal terms, maybe it's a
little bit positive, but when you adjust
for prices, consumers are falling
further and further behind, which is
exactly what the data shows, and it's
exactly what the data shows entering
recessionary periods. The six-month
change in real personal income excluding
transfer receipts was minus 0.9%. It's
actually a little bit worse when you go
back seven months. It's almost 1.2%.
Now, that doesn't sound like a lot. You
think, "Well, minus 1%." We're talking
economy-wide for just the private
private income, and the only times you
ever see a roughly minus 1% on a
six-month basis is in periods of either
recession or some big tax change where
everybody has to front-load their
payments into a year, and then the next
year incomes fall.
This is not It's clearly not the case.
We didn't see a the increase in 2025
that front-loaded a bunch of income. So,
we have the economic case where incomes
are falling off fast enough, it looks
like a recession. I mean, just look at
the chart on the screen. It shows you.
It looks It's going up, then it
flatlines, and now it's it's declining
in absolute terms. And it's not just
real personal income excluding
transfers. You see the same thing in
real disposable personal income. I
already mentioned top-line income. So,
the income data, powerful confirmation
at the very least. Whether you want to
argue the technical definition of
recession, whether or not the NBER is
going to declare it, something big
changed at the end of last year be- long
before we got to the energy shock, which
makes the energy shock that much more
dangerous because the classic case of an
energy shock recession is weak economy,
oil prices surge, and then suddenly the
bottom just falls out.
>> You know, speaking of bottom falling
out, if you look at the price of oil,
you all of a sudden we see it dropping,
you know, out of nowhere. And yet
there's no signs that, you know, the
conflict is really come to an end or
there's going to be a huge surge in a
lot of oil moving through the pipelines
or around the global economy. So, again,
talking about confirmation of the data
saying that consumers are pulling back
and demand for oil and energy is
dropping, and that's a huge red flag. We
also can look at interest rate market,
Jeff, because, you know, recently we
hear this every time interest rates go
up that, "Okay, this is the time, you
know. We're going to see 6, 7, 8, maybe
12% on the 30-year." And all of a
sudden, price starts to reverse. And yet
a lot of people don't understand. If
interest rates are going up, people have
to want to borrow at those higher
interest rates. And if their incomes are
going down, which is exactly what we're
seeing, and they're drawing down their
savings, again, exactly what we're
seeing, there's zero incentive. There's
nothing they're going to look and say,
"You know what? I really want to go buy
that new home or that new car and pay a
high interest rate." The reality is they
can't afford it. So, as we look around,
we're seeing all these confirmations
that, as you said, they're, you know,
the lower income group of the country,
they're definitely clearly in a
recession. The problem is it's slowly
filtering up into the middle class. And
the question then becomes if it gets
into the upper class where their
spending starts to get hit, well, watch
out. That K, as you said, it starts to
widen. Not Not the K itself, but the
number of people of that are falling
behind.
>> Well, let me give you another one where
it seems to be filtering upstairs.
Upstairs to the C-suite. Uh the
Conference Board's report on CEO
confidence and CEO feelings on the
economy just came out this past week,
too. Confidence among chief executive
officers about the US economy tumbled in
the second quarter as concerns
intensified about supply chains and
energy. The Conference Board's measure
of CEO confidence dropped to 47 from 59
in the first 3 months of the year,
according to results that were published
this past Thursday. Readings below 50
indicate more negative than positive
responses. And according to Dana
Peterson, who's the chief economist at
the Conference Board, CEOs reported that
the economy is materially worse now than
it was 6 months ago. There's your income
data right there. And expected economic
conditions to weaken further over the
next 6 months. There's your energy shock
right there. And nearly half of the
respondents said economic conditions
were worse, a dramatic swing from only
8% who said that in the first quarter of
this year. Now, not exactly surprising,
right, Steve? I mean, this is not
shocking data here because I mean, we
knew we knew energy shock and whatever
you thought the economy was doing before
March and April, the energy shock comes
along, oil prices surge, and that's
going to be a huge problem no matter
what. Even in a healthy economy, an
energy shock like that would be that's
going to knock something off the growth
rate. But when you have a fragile
economy that was already looking
recessionary in in very in several key
ways, suddenly energy shock comes along,
it's no surprise what the CEOs are
saying because they're they're going to
be seeing the the effects of it show up
pretty quickly.
>> Yeah, it seems like Jeff around April,
particularly with, you know, like Home
Depot and Lowe's, there's like something
happened in April. Yes, we can argue
easily that the labor market, you know,
started a recession back, you know, as
you said, in October of last year as
income started to fall below trend. But,
what about everybody else? There's
clearly So, something changed in April,
and obviously we know exactly what that
is. Is it energy prices stayed up too
high for too long? And that's always the
problem. In a strong economy, as you
said many times before, these energy
shocks, they can be absorbed, and they
can be absorbed for an extended period
of time. Sometimes long enough that the
economy can just move right past it,
energy prices come down, and everything
kind of booms. As you just said, the
risk right now is the economy's been
weak. It's weakening on top of that, and
the energy shock isn't going away. So,
this is now becoming a challenge,
particularly as we head into the summer,
where we know energy costs and demand
are going to be high, and that is a
problem because more consumers are going
to spend more money on gas, they're
going to spend more money cooling their
house, and that's going to mean less
money on vacations, less money filtering
out into all these businesses that are
very seasonal over the summer, they do
most of their business, they're not
going to see that as consumers pull
back. And that's a challenge, because
again, as we look, you know, ahead in
the months to come, the the outlook for
the economy doesn't get better. It seems
to be getting worse here.
>> Well, I think that, you know, one thing
that, um, certainly risky markets like
stocks are betting on that, okay, this
is all about the Iran conflict. If we
get the Iran conflict over with, we're
going to go right back to, you know,
healthy rainbows and unicorns,
everybody's going to be happy. So,
that's kind of one narrative that
doesn't really fit with the idea that
the economy was in maybe recessionary
shape going back to October of last
year. Because that what that would say
is
Iran didn't break this. Iran didn't
cause the labor market to go into
negative jobs, you know, job shedding
and negative job payroll growth or, you
know, uh employment, rising
unemployment, especially on an adjusted
basis, labor force drop I mean labor
force dropouts in in 2026 so far have
been absolutely huge, which again goes
along to the confirmation of what we're
getting from the income data. We already
saw that labor force dropouts were
accelerating this year, which goes along
with why we're seeing the income stats.
But if you think the Iran conflict broke
the economy, therefore a quick fix to
the Iran conflict ends the danger. But
another part of that too is right,
Steve? We talked about this last week,
the point of no return. The point of no
return in a healthy economy, you've got
lots of runway. There it's way down at
the end of the runway, you've got lots
of room, lots of a margin to absorb to
take the hit. But if the economy was
already on the cusp of a recession or
even in the same general vicinity of a
recession before the energy shock hits,
that point of no return suddenly is it's
right in your face. It's not way down
there, it's actually up here. And let me
throw some more data out here. I did a
video on this just yesterday. Canada
Canada reported a second straight
decline in GDP. Now, we don't care much
about technical definitions of
recessions, but when you see two
straight quarterly declines in GDP, the
fourth quarter of last year and the
first quarter of this year, it's tough
to get away from it. You know, people
can't ignore the technical definition of
recession. So, Canada, our closest
neighbor to the north saying, "Oh boy,
our economy was in rough shape long
before we got to the energy shock and
guess what? We're really concerned the
energy shock is going to make everything
worse." To the point that the Bank of
Canada has completely resisted the idea
of hiking rates, even though deep down,
you Steve, you know this, deep down they
would love to join their European
counterparts and say, "We're going to
hike rates. It's inflation, inflation,
inflation." The situation in Canada was
already bad to begin with and even the
Bank of Canada saying,
"We don't think we're going to be able
to hike rates." And with the latest data
coming in, it's more likely than not
they're going to start lowering rates,
which is what the bond market is doing,
which gets back to what Steve said
before. Interest rates are starting to
say
central banks are not even going to have
a chance to hike rates because we see
things breaking all over the place. In
fact, we see things breaking before we
even got to this year.
>> You know, Jeff, arguably the biggest
contrarian trade right now isn't the
market going up, which I think was
obviously one of them, you know, back in
in in April when I said, "Look, this is
the market was going to go higher."
Right now, the biggest contrarian trade
is going to be that interest rates are
going to go down because nobody sees
this happening and yet we're already
seeing it in the bond market. Rates are
coming down, prices are going up, and it
has everything to do with exactly
everything we're talking about. Workers
cannot afford higher interest rates, so
demand for rates goes or demand for
lending products go down, and then if
you're a business of lending, which is
what banks are doing, you're not going
to raise your rates in this market,
you're going to have to push rates down.
You're going to see banks buying more
bonds to bring rates down because there
is no other outcome. And this is
interesting because you look forward to
June, as you mentioned, that, you know,
not long ago the central bankers wanted
to hike rates. That was the base case.
We're going to get another hike, and
then, as you said, the curve suggested
that they would be cutting in the months
to come. And now, all of a sudden, it's
starting to look really clear that
they're not going to hike, they're going
to panic. Maybe they won't cut in June,
but the messaging is going to change in
a big way that all of a sudden they're
nervous. Market's not going to love
their nervousness. Now, stocks are
because they're going to say, "Hey, if
they're nervous, it means they're going
to cut rates, all is going to come
down." And yes, you can see this point
where the stock market booms while the
economy is weakening. It doesn't mean
the market's going to stay up a long
time if that happens. You get these
blow-off scenarios. But the bigger risk
here isn't that lower interest rates are
going to stimulate the economy, that
there again, another validation point
that yes, we entered recession back in
October, the economy is weakening, the
tax cuts weren't enough to push us
through this energy shock, and now this
is becoming real and that the point of
no return maybe closer. We may have
passed it. We don't know yet, but the
bond market here is telling us very
clearly central bankers are wrong, going
to have to cut here and it's probably
not going to work.
>> Yeah, that's I mean blow-off top point
of no return blow-off top. Yeah, so the
Iran conflict plus central bankers,
right? Because those are the two sources
of danger from the equity markets
perspective, right? Central banks hiking
rate Oh, stocks hates hate rate hikes.
Uh the Iran conflict potential So, if
you end up with the Iran conflict being
resolved plus central bankers suddenly
saying we're not going to hike rates,
yeah, S&P 7 S&P 8,000 S&P 9,000 S&P
10,000 I mean, right?
Uh that's but then the real implication
is okay.
You know, I talked about this yesterday.
You and I were talking about this before
we started recording. The Bank of
England. The Bank of England was one of
the most hawkish central banks as soon
as the energy shock started. It started
right back in March. March the Bank of
England said, "You know what? There's a
good chance we're going to hike rates at
a even if their next meeting in April,
but if not April, by June for sure." And
then what happens this past week? As the
economic data in England looks even
worse than the data that we just went
over for the US or Canada, suddenly the
governor of the Bank of England a fellow
by the name of Andrew Bailey comes out
and says, "You know what?
I think we're going to tolerate some
inflation here." And you never hear
that. Central banks never say that. They
never say we're going to tolerate
inflation because they the deep-seated
inflation bias there's No, we never
tolerate inflation. Inflation is the
worst thing that we ever we think that
that there can be except for
unemployment. So, Bank of England, one
of the most hawkish regimes out there
suddenly changes its tune to say, "We're
going to tolerate inflation." What he's
saying is, "Oh, crap. We were wrong
about the inflation stuff. The economy
is actually looking a lot more like the
classic energy shock case, which means
we're facing higher unemployment that
looks a lot more like the recession that
just showed up in the US income data and
is going to show up in a lot more places
beyond just the US and Canada. The
recession case isn't quite confirmed,
but we keep getting more and more data
that shows that that's the most likely
outcome, including central bankers
saying, "We're going to tolerate
inflation."